A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Civic Interests, Series D FA313
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Tarrytown Projects
  - Tarrytown Projects - Tarrytown and North Tarrytown - Miscellaneous
    - Tarrytown Projects - Tarrytown and North Tarrytown - Miscellaneous, 1955-1961 (Box 42, Folder 327)
    - Tarrytown Projects - Tarrytown and North Tarrytown - Miscellaneous, 1949-1958 (Box 42, Folder 327A)
  - Tarrytown Projects - Tarrytown and North Tarrytown - Miscellaneous Projects - Civilian Defense, 1942-1954 (Box 42, Folder 328)
    Financed in Tarrytown in 1942 by public appeal. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. made contribution. John D. Rockefeller 3rd and Laurance S. Rockefeller refused participation in Civil Defense in 1953 since principal residence not in Westchester. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
  - Tarrytown Projects - Tarrytown and North Tarrytown - Miscellaneous Projects - Highland Manor Property Park Project, 1943, 1943-1949 (Box 42, Folder 329)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributes toward purchase of property and creation of Patriots' Park. Background of tax struggle. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard.
  - Tarrytown Projects - Tarrytown and North Tarrytown - Miscellaneous Projects - Housing, 1937-1938 (Box 42, Folder 330)
    Representatives of Tarrytown ask for loan to build apartments for General Motors workers and clear slums. Investigated by Jay Downer, refused. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Jay Downer.
  - Tarrytown Projects - Tarrytown and North Tarrytown - Miscellaneous Projects - List of Contributions to Tarrytown and Westchester Activities, 1879-1966 (Box 42, Folder 331)
  - Tarrytown Projects - Tarrytown and North Tarrytown - Miscellaneous Projects - Materne Case, 1943-1944 (Box 42, Folder 332)
    V. P. Materne, town supervisor, cashed town checks to $12,000 for his own benefit. Caught, jailed. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributed to fund to help pay off Materne's debt to bonding company. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., V. P. Materne, S. C. Mastick.
  - Tarrytown Projects - Tarrytown and North Tarrytown - Miscellaneous Projects - North Tarrytown Parent-Teacher Association, 1938-1956 (Box 42, Folder 333)
    Contributions.
  - Tarrytown Projects - Tarrytown and North Tarrytown - Miscellaneous Projects - Tarrytown Parent-Teacher Association, 1934-1957 (Box 42, Folder 334)
  - Tarrytown Projects - Tarrytown and North Tarrytown - Miscellaneous Projects - Tarrytown Railroad Station Park, 1935-1954 (Box 42, Folder 335)
    Request that John D. Rockefeller, Jr. buy bonds to finance project. Depot Plaza. No result in this file.
  - Tarrytown Projects - Taxpayers Association of the Town of Mount Pleasant, 1935-1939 (Box 42, Folder 336)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. refuses to join Taxpayers Association or join in litigation for return of taxes. No real reasons given here. Correspondents include Thomas M. Debevoise, Charles O. Heydt.
    77.1
  - Tarrytown Projects - Tarrytown School - New Site and Building, 1936-1949 (Box 42, Folder 337)
    Consideration of various sites (including Elsie Janiss property). County Historical Society objected to use of Janis' property. Voters in election voted out Janiss property. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. financed further surveys. Issue continued through 1948. No conclusion shown in file. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Jay Downer, Arthur W. Packard.
    77.3
  - Tarrytown Projects - Tarrytown School - Consolidation Survey, 1946-1952 (Box 43, Folder 338)
    Move to consolidate schools in Pocantico Hills, Elmsford, Irvington and Tarrytown. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. made several offers to assist in building new schools. Local politics kept things unhinged. No resolution in this file. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard.
    77.31
  - Tarrytown Projects - Tarrytown School Site, 1950-1955 (Box 43, Folder 339)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. offers up to $300,000 to purchase site for new consolidated schools. Issue blocked by local groups. Discussed for four years. School board won final victory for consolidation, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledge called. Schools built. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., W. J. Yates.
    77.32
  - Tarrytown Projects - Tarrytown School Site - 1950 Gift for Irving Site, 1950-1955 (Box 43, Folder 340)
    Pledge of $250,000 increased to $300,000 after delay before voter approval.
  - Tarrytown Projects - Tarrytown School Site - 1955 Gift Toward Construction, 1955-1956 (Box 43, Folder 341)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $350,000 toward construction of consolidated high school.
  - Tarrytown Projects - North Tarrytown Tax Survey, 1938-1939 (Box 43, Folder 342)
    Tax Foundation study of taxes in Tarrytown. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. finances a booklet called "Tax Facts" showing costs of government. Ideas on how to cut taxes in this file. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Jay Downer.
    77.4
  - Tarrytown Projects - Tarrytown Consolidation - Reed Survey, 1946-1949 (Box 43, Folder 343)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. employs Thomas Reed, government expert, to study possibilities of consolidating Tarrytown and other communities. Making the Study did not commit John D. Rockefeller, Jr. or anyone to even consider its recommendations. Copy of report included. No apparent action resulted. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, T. D. Reed.
    77.5
  - Tarrytown Projects - Tarrytown Consolidation - Reed Survey - Publicity, 1946-1958 (Box 43, Folder 344)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s arrangements for announcing report and releasing study through Tarrytown Daily News. Satisfaction with publicity. Clippings. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Wallace Odell.
  - Tarrytown Projects - Tarrytown Consolidation - Reed Survey - Clippings, 1946-1956 (Box 44, Folder 345)
  - Tarrytown Projects - Tarrytown Charter Commission, 1946-1950 (Box 44, Folder 346)
    Study of consolidation of Tarrytown resulting from Reed Survey. Town commission produces charter, Governor Dewey vetoes bill which would have put charter before people for a test. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pays some of the expenses of the Commission after Dewey's veto. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Mr. Daniel contributed to second round of negotiations, aid in publicity for referendum. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard.
    77.51
  - Tarrytown Projects - Tarrytown Charter Commission, 1946-1950 (Box 44, Folder 0346A)
  - Tarrytown Projects - Hudson River Bridge and Thruway, 1935-1952 (Box 44, Folder 347)
    Proposed bridge. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s concern of damage to scenic beauty. Bridge built. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Jay Downer.
    77.6
  - Tarrytown Projects - Hudson River Speech Center, 1939-1961 (Box 44, Folder 348)
    To help children with speech difficulties. Becomes part of Phelps Memorial Hospital. Mary French Rockefeller's interest. Correspondents include John S. Wortley, Dana S. Creel.
    77.8
  - Tarrytown Projects - Civic and Business Association of North Tarrytown, 1949-1955 (Box 44, Folder 349)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. honorary member. Group activities. Family contributions. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard.
    77.7
- United States Government
  - United States Government - General
    Nelson A. Rockefeller's interest in WPA art project. Roosevelt asks his support. Nelson A. Rockefeller in State Department in 1942. Universal registration, activity in war effort, propaganda, morale Organizations, OPA, correspondence. Dean Rusk accepting Trusteeship in Rockefeller Foundation. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. supports Dean Acheson's foreign policy. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s opinions on appeasement and the Korean War. John D. Rockefeller 3rd attends State Department meeting of Foundation executives interested in overseas work. Laurance S. Rockefeller gives $3,000 to study of Federal Government employees. Papers on tariffs, agriculture, foreign policy. John D. Rockefeller 3rd's interest in United States Information Agency. Requests for Rockefeller support of Administration policy. Eisenhower's request for Rockefeller support of Mutual Security Program. Refugees. International Conference. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Cordell Hull, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Dean Rusk, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Laurance S. Rockefeller, Dana S. Creel, Dwight D. Eisenhower.
    92
    - United States Government - General, 1936-1950 (Box 44, Folder 350)
    - United States Government - General, 1950-1958 (Box 45, Folder 351)
    - United States Government - General, 1953-1955 (Box 45, Folder 352)
    - United States Government - General, 1951-1960 (Box 45, Folder 353)
    - United States Government - General, 1951-1960 (Box 45, Folder 353A)
      David Rockefeller supports liberal trade policy for importing art. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
    - United States Government - General, 1958-1961 (Box 46, Folder 354)
    - United States Government - General, 1958-1961 (Box 46, Folder 354A)
  - United States Government - State Department Far East Conference, October 1949, 1949-1971 (Box 46, Folder 355)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd participates in round table, confidential discussion of China. John D. Rockefeller 3rd's views expressed in conference.
  - United States Government - Nelson A. Rockefeller - Correspondence, 1939-1942 (Box 46, Folder 356)
    1941 - Nelson A. Rockefeller on use of family pictures, pay for assistants, thanks for aid in preparing speeches, forwarding mail to Washington. 1942 - Requests for Latin American jobs with Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs (CIAA) made to New York office. Appearances declined by Nelson A. Rockefeller. Plans for aiding war effort. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard.
    92.1
  - United States Government - Nelson A. Rockefeller - Correspondence, 1943-1946, 1958 (Box 46, Folder 357)
    1943 - Nelson A. Rockefeller makes New York arrangements for "dark skin" delegations. Nelson A. Rockefeller's November 26, 1943 address at American Legion Dinner on meaning of Inter-American Cooperation. 1944 - Nelson A. Rockefeller's Pan American suggestions, telegrams to House Appropriations Committee. Requests for information, job applications. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard.
  - United States Government - Nelson A. Rockefeller - Washington Clippings, 1940-1943 (Box 46, Folder 358)
  - United States Government - W. O. Inglis - History of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs (CIAA), 1941-1947 (Box 47, Folder 359)
    Copy of work. Correspondents include W. O. Inglis, John E. Lockwood.
  - United States Government - W. O. Inglis - History of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs (CIAA) - Correspondence, 1941-1947 (Box 47, Folder 360)
    Correspondents include W. O. Inglis, John E. Lockwood.
  - United States Government - Nelson A. Rockefeller - Hemispheric Program, 1941-1944 (Box 47, Folder 361)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s letters to Nelson A. Rockefeller and others about Nelson A. Rockefeller's work as Coordination of Inter-American Affairs. Comments on Nelson A. Rockefeller's knowledge and ability in office. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Nelson A. Rockefeller.
  - United States Government - Nelson A. Rockefeller - State Department Appointment, 1944-1945 (Box 47, Folder 362)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. letters replying to best wishes expressed to him on Nelson A. Rockefeller's appointment as Assistant Secretary of State.
    92.2
  - United States Government - Hoover Commission Report, 1948-1953 (Box 47, Folder 363)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller served as an advisor on Public Works Task Force of Hoover Commission. Robert Moses was Chairman. No real discussion of the issues in this file. Clippings, booklets on work of commission. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard, Robert Moses.
    92.3
  - United States Government - Hoover Commission Report, 1948-1949 (Box 47, Folder 364)
  - United States Government - Citizens Committee on Reorganization of Federal Government, 1949-1960 (Box 48, Folder 365)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Nelson A. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd became members of committee to work for implementation of Hoover Commission proposals. Made contributions to work of Committee. Appeals for family support of Citizens committee. All declined. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Laurance S. Rockefeller, Nelson A. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    92.31
  - United States Government - Citizens Committee on Reorganization of Federal Government, 1949-1960 (Box 48, Folder 0365A)
  - United States Government - Citizens Committee on Reorganization of Federal Government - Contributions, 1949-1953 (Box 48, Folder 366)
    Recommendations, transmittal, and receipt of contributions.
  - United States Government - Citizens Committee on Reorganization of Federal Government - Printed Matter, 1949-1958 (Box 48, Folder 367)
    Published by Citizens Committee.
  - United States Government - Point Four Program, 1950-1955 (Box 48, Folder 368)
    Advisory Board for International Development. Nelson A. Rockefeller appointed chairman of Advisory Board by Harry S. Truman. Submission of report "Partners in Progress" to the President. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, Thomas M. Debevoise.
    92.4
  - United States Government - Dulles Mission-Japanese Peace Mission, 1951-1959 (Box 48, Folder 369)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd appointed to mission to prepare Japanese peace treaty in 1951. Traveled with John F. Dulles to Japan. Notes on Japan and Japanese. Criticisms of American occupation policies an Okinawa. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, J. F. Dulles, Dean Rusk.
    92.5
  - United States Government - Dulles Mission-Japanese Peace Mission - Clippings, 1951 (Box 48, Folder 370)
    Newspaper accounts of Peace Mission efforts.
  - United States Government - Dulles Mission-Japanese Peace Mission - Catholic Controversy, 1951 (Box 49, Folder 371)
    Criticism of John D. Rockefeller 3rd by Catholic reporter for failure to meet with Japanese Catholics. John D. Rockefeller 3rd explained reasons why satisfactorily.
  - United States Government - Dulles Mission-Japanese Peace Mission - United States-Japanese Cultural Relations - Report to Ambassador Dulles, 1951 (Box 49, Folder 372)
    Report dated April 15, 1951.
  - United States Government - Dulles Mission-Japanese Peace Mission - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Report, 1951-1958 (Box 49, Folder 373)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd prepared report for John F. Dulles on cultural exchange between United States and Japan. Comments on drafts of reports by authorities on Japan. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, John F. Dulles.
  - United States Government - Dulles Mission-Japanese Peace Mission - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Report - Correspondence with Dulles, 1950-1951 (Box 49, Folder 374)
    Preparation and comments on John D. Rockefeller 3rd's report on cultural relations with Japan.
  - United States Government - Dulles Mission-Japanese Peace Mission - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Report - Cultural Material from Japan, 1951 (Box 49, Folder 375)
    Suggestions from Japanese scholars for improving United States-Japanese relations.
  - United States Government - Government Affairs Foundation, 1953-1957 (Box 49, Folder 376)
    Organized by Nelson A. Rockefeller to improve the science of government and administration of public affairs. Frank C. Moore chosen to head organization. Rodman Rockefeller a director. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller.
    92.6
  - United States Government - Government Affairs Foundation, 1953-1957 (Box 49, Folder 0376A)
    David Rockefeller made gifts to foundation. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - United States Government - Department of Health, Education and Welfare, 1953-1961 (Box 49, Folder 377)
    Clippings. John D. Rockefeller 3rd declines to become trustee of National Institute of Health. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    92.7
  - United States Government - U.S. Civil Service Commission - Career Development Conference, 1961 (Box 50, Folder 378)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd made funds available for conference at Princeton of representatives of universities and federal government to discuss more effective public service. Correspondents include D. McLean, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    92.8
- Westchester County Charter
  - Westchester County Charter, 1926-1942 (Box 50, Folder 379)
    Recurrent attempts to revamp form of government in Westchester. John D. Rockefeller, Sr. contributed to defeat of proposed change in 1927. Copy of charter as approved by voters in 1937; put into effect in 1939. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Sr., Nelson A. Rockefeller, Thomas M. Debevoise.
    10
- Westchester County Research Bureau
  - Westchester County Research Bureau, 1910-1930 (Box 50, Folder 380)
    Appeals to John D. Rockefeller, Sr., John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to participate in organization for betterment of County government. John D. Rockefeller, Sr. contributed to program 1911-1918. New efforts of organization in 1920's were not aided by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Sr., John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Kenneth Chorley, Starr J. Murphy, V. E. Macy, O. G. Cartright, J. Allen.
    83
- Westchester County Organizations
  - Westchester County Organizations - Westchester County Boards, 1940-1950 (Box 50, Folder 381)
    Information on developments in Westchester. Flood control, recruiting WACs, appeals for small contributions, shopping centers. Some contributions made. Schools, first aid corps, libraries, United Fund, etc. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    76
  - Westchester County Organizations - Westchester County Boards, 1940-1950 (Box 50, Folder 381A)
  - Westchester County Organizations - Westchester County Boards, 1940-1962 (Box 51, Folder 382)
  - Westchester County Organizations - Westchester County Boards, 1940-1962 (Box 51, Folder 382A)
  - Westchester County Organizations - Westchester County Boards - Ruth Taylor Retirement and Award Fund, 1950-1955 (Box 51, Folder 383)
    Special fund initiated by Nelson A. Rockefeller to provide scholarships in welfare and health annually. Done in honor of Ruth Taylor who was Westchester Welfare commissioner for 20 years.
  - Westchester County Organizations - Tarrytown-Mt. Pleasant Budget, 1932-1939 (Box 51, Folder 384)
    Nelson A. Rockefeller's interest in town management, sample town budgets. Analysis of budget by Chase bank accountants. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller.
  - Westchester County Organizations - Westchester County Taxpayers Association, 1932-1939 (Box 51, Folder 385)
    Program to cut expenses and taxes. Nelson A. Rockefeller refuses invitation to become director. Family withholds support because of possibility of adverse reactions. Association criticized by several segments of the population. Later called Civic League of Westchester. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard, Robert W. Gumbel, E. M. Allen.
    76.1
  - Westchester County Organizations - Civic League of Westchester, 1941-1947 (Box 51, Folder 386)
    Formerly Westchester County Taxpayers Association. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. made annual $100 contribution. Worked to reduce county budget. Improve county services. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Westchester County Organizations - Civic League of Westchester - Contributions, 1941-1947 (Box 51, Folder 387)
    Formerly Westchester County Taxpayers Association. Record of payments.
  - Westchester County Organizations - Westchester County Department of Health, 1932-1938 (Box 51, Folder 388)
    Problems of Public Health in Westchester. Nelson A. Rockefeller becomes member in 1932 of the County Board of Health. Nelson A. Rockefeller provides anonymous assistance in charity cases. Rodman Rockefeller joins Board. Search for successor to Dr. Matthias Nicoll, who served as Commissioner. Activities. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard, Ernest L. Stebbins, Arthur Jones, William A. Holla.
    76.2
  - Westchester County Organizations - Westchester County Department of Health, 1941-1959 (Box 51, Folder 389)
    Problems of Public Health in Westchester. Nelson A. Rockefeller becomes member in 1932 of the County Board of Health. Nelson A. Rockefeller provides anonymous assistance in charity cases. Rodman Rockefeller joins Board. Activities. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard, Ernest L. Stebbins, Arthur Jones, William A. Holla.
  - Westchester County Organizations - Westchester County Medical Society, 1943-1955 (Box 52, Folder 390)
    Plans for clinic, Rockefeller aid sought. Charter for Academy of Medicine formed. Correspondents include William A. Kelly, Boyden Roseberry, Arthur Jones.
    76.22
  - Westchester County Organizations - Westchester County Association, 1943-1957 (Box 52, Folder 391)
    Proposed association, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. declines participation in group, fizzled. Second try 1949. Various projects. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Gustavus T. Kirby.
    76.3
  - Westchester County Organizations - Westchester County Association, 1943-1957 (Box 52, Folder 0391A)
    David Rockefeller's contribution. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - Westchester County Organizations - Mental Hygiene Association of Westchester County, 1944-1961 (Box 52, Folder 392)
    Name changed to Mental Health Association of Westchester County. Requests for contributions. Reports on activities. Anonymous contribution. Later requests declined. Blanchette H. Rockefeller's contributions. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Mrs. John Bingham, Norman P. Davis, Narcissa V. Street.
    76.4
  - Westchester County Organizations - Mental Hygiene Association of Westchester County, 1944-1961 (Box 52, Folder 0392A)
    Name changed to Mental Health Association of Westchester County. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - Westchester County Organizations - Westchester County Department of Planning, 1946-1961 (Box 52, Folder 393)
    Slum conditions in Westchester. Charter revisions. Zoning. Correspondents include W. Lindquist, Hugh Pomeroy.
    76.5
  - Westchester County Organizations - Westchester County Department of Planning, 1946-1961 (Box 52, Folder 0393A)
  - Westchester County Organizations - Westchester County Department of Planning - Special Study of Impacts on Residential Neighborhoods, 1950-1953 (Box 52, Folder 394)
    Constitution and By-Laws. David Rockefeller pledge for Impact Study.
  - Westchester County Organizations - Westchester County Department of Planning - Meetings, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 395)
    Various projects, studies made on recreation highway, watershed, etc. Correspondents include Hugh R. Pomeroy, W. T. Lindquist.
  - Westchester County Organizations - Westchester County Department of Planning - Meetings, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 0395A)
  - Westchester County Organizations - Westchester County Department of Planning - Reports, 1956-1961 (Box 53, Folder 396)
    Various reports.
  - Westchester County Organizations - Westchester Citizens' Housing Council, Inc., 1957-1961 (Box 53, Folder 397)
    Organization is recommended by Westchester County Council of Social Agencies. Committee for better housing conditions. Activities. Report of the Committee on Housing. Correspondents include Paul R. Reynolds.
    76.6